本字幕由大家字幕組原創翻譯制作僅供學習 禁止用于任何商業盈利行為若因私自散布傳播造成法律問題 本字幕組概不負責更多影視請搜索并關注新浪微博  大家字幕組
翻譯： 肉肉  叉叉美少年  羽
安妮 博林承諾為亨利八世誕下男性子嗣
以此 國王承諾給她第一夫人之位
他不顧教皇及整個基督世界的反對
強行為安妮戴上王后冕冠
翻譯： 抹茶蘇 漢謨拉 小俊仔兒
1533年秋 安妮和她的新生兒一同返回了白廳
卻是一個女孩
時間軸&特效：嬌嬌 靜宇 期待跑600的Sandra  壓制：太陽雨 大汪不開森
校對：我是小鮮肉
第1季 第4集
狼·廳
她身體健康嗎
Healthy?
很健康 陛下
Yes, Your Majesty.
為她冠名 伊麗莎白
Call her Elizabeth.
取消騎士們的競技比武
Cancel the jousts.
- 他只字未問王后的情況如何  - 現在已經無關緊要了 不是嗎
- He didn't ask how the Queen was.  - Hardly matters now, does it?
我覺得她是餓了
I think she was hungry.
我女兒要去住在哈特菲爾德
My daughter is to live at Hatfield.
是的
Yes.
我覺得西班牙人瑪麗的家庭應該被拆分開
I think Spanish Mary's household should be broken up.
她能成為我女兒家里的一份子
She can become a member of my daughter's household.
作為什么樣的存在
In the capacity of?
作為我女兒的女傭
In the capacity of my daughter's servant.
不然她還能是什么
What else can she be?
沒必要有偽裝的平等
There can be no pretence of equality.
瑪麗態度傲慢且令人討厭
Mary is a bastard.
廢物要利用 事態主次順序也要維護
Waste can be saved and the proper order of things asserted.
與此同時 我要你去一趟法國
Meanwhile, I want you to go to France.
我要為我的女兒和一位法國王子定親
I want a marriage contract for my daughter. A French prince.
- 斯蒂芬 伽得納他... - 你今天對我的話好像有很多意見
- Stephen Gardiner is...  - You're very unwilling today.
你是不喜歡法國嗎
You don't like the French?
那或許你會愿意和羅馬皇帝去談結盟
Perhaps you would prefer an alliance with the Emperor?
你和他的親信關系很好 不是嗎
You're very friendly with his man, aren't you?
沙皮？
Chapuys?
沒別的事我就告辭了 王后
If that will be all, Your Majesty?
嗯
Hmm.
你為何不把那女孩買下
Why don't you ask for her?
西摩家族很窮
The Seymours are poor.
他們會很樂意將她賣給你的
They'll sell her to you happily.
你誤會了我的興趣所在
You mistake my interest.
呵呵呵 把你的謊話留著在下議院的時候說吧 你騙不到我的
Oh, fah-la-la! Tell your lies to the Commons, not to me.
我能看透很多事情
I see things.
你和我 我們都要特別留心
You and me, we keep our eyes open.
我能留心注意到一些你目不能及的地方
I could keep my eyes open in places you cannot go.
比如說 安妮的房間里
In Anne's rooms, for example.
每次傳召外人的時候 她都在做禱告
When you call you'll find her at prayer,
為乞丐女人縫衣服
sewing a smock for a beggar woman.
可您以為這是事情真相嗎
Do you think that's what's really going on?
你覺得她真的能拋棄那些年輕機靈的男寵們嗎
Do you think she's given up all her nimble young men?
能拋棄那些贊頌她的美麗的十四行詩嗎
All those sonnets in praise of her beauty?
但現在有國王為她贊頌了
She has the King to praise her now.
除非她能再次懷上龍種 否則她將獨守深宮了
She'll get no praise from him until she has a ripe belly again.
難道有什么阻礙嗎
And what would hinder that?
沒事...如果他能讓她再次懷上的話
Nothing...if he's up to it.
你說話小心點
Careful.
那個小賤人就這樣進進出出宮里的每個房間
And that little sneak is for ever in and out of every room,
像是要為所有年輕男子們做媒一樣
acting as a go-between for all the gallants.
- 噢 我看那小男孩挺好的啊  - 他根本不知道自己的處境
- Oh, I see no harm in the boy.  - He doesn't know his place.
他只是個跳梁小丑 在拼命把握機會
He's a jumped-up nobody, taking his chance
因為這是個混亂的時代
because the times are disordered.
呵 我想你也可以完全這么評價我的 羅奇福德夫人
Well, I suppose you could say the same thing about me, Lady Rochford,
我也想相信你會的
and I'm sure you do.
王后在任何地方都能看到敵人
The Queen sees enemies everywhere.
本就如此
So she should.
所有人都在等著她失勢下位
They're waiting for her to fail.
她說她會為亨利生下王子
She's said she'll give Henry a son,
但如果她做不到 所有的古老家族們都會反戈一擊
so if she doesn't, all the old families are waiting their turn.
- 我們的圣女怎么樣了  - 十分受歡迎
- How's our Holy Maid?  - Popular.
她說抹大拉的瑪麗亞給她一封純金鑲裹的信
Mary Magdalene sent her a letter, illuminated in gold.
有訪客？
Visitors?
讓她進來
Bring her in.
你說你可以在天堂、地獄和煉獄中自由穿梭？
You say that you can roam through Heaven, Hell and Purgatory?
那你一定見過惡魔咯
And have you seen the Devil also?
他長相如何
And how did he look?
像一只大鳥
Like a bird.
呵 那可真是松了口氣
That's a relief.
你太天真了
You think so?
他惡臭難當
He stinks!
他的利爪上血屎斑斑
He's got claws smeared with blood and shit.
他有一次化身年輕的俊美男子
He came to me once as a young man...
勾引我
to tempt me.
占我便宜
Pawing at me.
那你呢 受了勾引沒
And were you? Tempted?
我可不會屈服撒旦的
I'm not for Satan.
- 我一拒絕了他 他就向我吐口水 - 他可真沒教養
- When I rejected him he spat in my face.  - No manners.
我拿紙巾擦去
I wiped it off with a napkin.
是一團黑色的 冒著地獄惡臭的
It's black, with the stench of Hell...
腐爛物
..something rotting.
那東西現在在哪
And where is it now?
在多姆 愛德華那里
Dom Edwards has it.
- 難道他要讓人們買票參觀嗎  - 是當作祭品
- And does he show it to people for money?  - For offerings.
你說國王一旦娶了安妮夫人
You said that the King wouldn't reign one month
就不會在位超過一個月
after he married Lady Anne.
可是...
Well...
數月過去了 安妮夫人成了王后
the months have passed and the Lady Anne is queen
還給國王生下了孩子
and has given the King a child.
所以呢...你現在還有什么可說的？
So...what do you say now?
我只能說 在上帝眼中
I say, in the eyes of God,
他已經不再是國王了 甚至比不上這個大主教的地位
he's no more the real king than HE is the real archbishop.
這就是你們叛變的正當理由嗎
Then would it be justified to raise a rebellion against him?
暗殺他 再另尋君主？
Assassinate him? Put another in his place?
你覺得呢
What do you think?
在所有可能的金雀花王朝候選家族中
Of the possible Plantagenet claimants to the throne
你選擇了考特尼家族 而不是波蘭人
you've chosen the Courtenay family, not the Poles.
埃克塞特侯爵 亨利  而不是蒙塔古勛爵 亨利
Henry, Marquis of Exeter, not Henry, Lord Montague,
- 還是你把他們倆搞混了   - 當然沒有
- or do you get them mixed up?  - Of course not.
這兩位紳士及他們的夫人 我都見過了
I've met both of those gentlemen. I've met their wives.
還見過了費舍爾主教 他們都站在我這邊
I've met Bishop Fisher. They all come to me.
考特尼家族是傳承自愛德華國王的女兒一脈
Now, Courtenay descends from a daughter of King Edward.
蒙塔古則是傳承自他的哥哥
Montague from his brother.
你如何把他們的利益需求安排妥當呢
How would you sort out their claims?
還是說讓他們自己爭出個結果呢
Or would you let them scrap it out?
如果想掀起一場戰爭的話
It's good to have a few kings and queens in reserve
多預留幾個國王王后是很有必要的 對嗎
if you are going to start a war.
噢 沒必要嫌棄戰爭的
Oh, no need of a war.
天將降大禍于英格蘭
God is sending a plague to England.
- 不出半年 亨利和那個臭婊子都會命喪黃泉   - 我呢？
- Henry will be dead in six months and so will his whore.  - And me?
不止你 這個屋子里的人 無一幸免
And you. And everyone in this room.
只有你會安然無恙嗎
Except you?
那我的侄女 愛麗絲
And my niece, Alice,
誰又能確保你們周全呢
who has done you no harm?
你房子里的所有女人都是異教徒
All the women of your house are heretics.
災禍將使之灰飛煙滅
The plague will rot them all.
我們太遷就著她了 她在嘲笑我們的懦弱
We're too soft with her. She's laughing at us.
她很快就會坦白了
She's close to confessing.
- 你怎么會知道的    - 我侄女昨晚一直陪著她
- What makes you think that?  - Because my niece is with her at night.
看見她因為每天騙人而暗自哭泣
She cries because she knows she's a fraud.
然后將眼淚從眼皮下拭去
Then she peeps out from under her eyelids
看看她的眼淚里有些什么
to see the effect her tears have had.
相信我吧 她會坦白的  我打算把她的追隨者都帶回來
Trust me, she'll confess. I want to start bringing in her followers.
- 托馬斯 莫爾？  -不 他沒參與這件事
- Thomas More?  - No, he's clear of this.
那她之前提到的其他人呢 費舍爾大主教 埃克塞特夫人 波蘭人
The others she mentioned? Bishop Fisher, Lady Exeter, the Poles?
我會處理好的
I'll deal with them myself.
在這片土地上 還有一些很有影響力的人
They are some of the most powerful people in the land.
是嘛 我也會用我最好的態度的
Well, then, I'll be on my best behaviour.
- 大主教閣下  - 本尼迪克特  - 你怎可如此大意？
- My Lord Bishop.  - Benedic...  - Why are you so gullible?
你最好能祈求國王的原諒
You'd better ask the King's forgiveness.
-請他看在你年老體弱的份上 從輕發落  - 我無意冒犯
- Plead old age. Infirmity.  - I don't know my offence.
無論你怎么想 我都沒有重頭再來的機會了
And, whatever you think, I am not in my second childhood.
我認為你有
I think you are.
為什么你如此愿意相信伊麗莎白 巴頓
Why else would you have given such credence to Elizabeth Barton?
因為當她說出這些話的時候 她有滿腔熱血
Because when she speaks, she is inspired.
我也看到了抹大拉的瑪麗
With my own eyes I have seen a golden letter
發送的金色信件
sent by Mary Magdalene...
抹大拉的瑪麗 哈 不過事實上 這是博金教父撰寫的
Mary Magdalene, yes. Actually it was written by Father Bocking.
一個叫威廉 霍克赫斯特的僧侶
The gilding is by a monk.
給它鍍的金
One William Hawkhurst.
我們還知道 在大人上任之前
And we know that before the Lord goes about his work,
通過周圍的仆人們 發布了律己令
he gives a warning of himself through his servants.
阿莫斯先知可都沒有做到這樣...
For is it not stated by the prophet Amos...
拜托 請不要在我面前稱呼阿莫斯為先知
Please, don't prophet Amos me.
巴頓威脅了國王 擅自揣測了他的生死
Barton threatened the King. She foresaw his death.
預知這結果和渴望著結果 可不是一個概念
Foreseeing is not the same as desiring.
她與國王的敵人為伍
She sat down with the King's enemies
并慫恿他們取國王而代之
and told them they would be king.
如果你指的是埃克塞特  為何你不親自跟他談呢
If you mean Exeter, why don't you speak to him?
不過 埃克塞特并沒有公開反對國王
Well, Exeter's not been writing against the King.
-你卻有   - 證據呢 拿出來看看
- You have.  - Where? Show me?
你在國外的那些印刷匠們 他們很不錯 現在正在為我效力了
Your printers abroad, they're very good. They're working for me now.
去年六月 正值王后加冕大慶
In June last year, just after the Queen was crowned,
你的兒子蒙塔古勛爵 和你的兒子杰弗里 波利 與瑪麗夫人共進晚餐
your son Lord Montague and your son Geoffrey Pole dined with Lady Mary.
半月之后 又一次進餐
Two weeks later, they dined with her again.
我著實好奇他們談了些什么
I wonder what they discussed?
你當然會好奇
I'm sure you do.
事實上 我并沒有
Actually, no, I don't.
在廚房幫忙扛蘆筍的孩子 是我的人
The boy who carried in the asparagus, that was my boy.
切杏仁的孩子 也也是我的人
The boy who cut the apricots, he was mine, too.
那時的日子過得是那么自在舒心  不過一去不復返了
Holy simplicity was all very well in its day, but its day is over.
我們現在可是被卷入了戰爭中
We're at war.
不能僅僅因為國王的士兵們未曾攻陷街道
Just because the Emperor's soldiers aren't running down the street,
就自欺欺人
don't deceive yourself.
這是一場戰爭 而你 身在敵營
This is a war and you're in the enemy camp.
他們在談論王位 談到入侵
They talked about the Emperor, about the invasion,
商討事半功倍的妙計
about the best way to bring it about.
正如你所見 瑪格麗特夫人
So, you see, Lady Margaret...
我對你的一家可謂是仁至義盡了
..your family owes much to my forbearance.
夫人 寫信給國王 乞求他的原諒吧
Write to the King, my lady, beg his forgiveness.
告訴他你是那么的天真 那么容易受人欺騙
Tell him you are exceptionally easy to mislead.
告訴他 你腦子里都生蟲了
Tell him that you don't have the brain of a flea.
卑躬屈膝去乞求原諒
Grovel.
我現在終于知道沃爾西當初為何要留著你了
I see why Wolsey retained you.
你們都是一丘之貉
You are a ruffian, and so was he.
看你是病的不輕了 回床躺著吧
Fall ill. Take to your bed.
這是我的建議
That's what I recommend.
真是難以置信 他們居然會背叛我
It's hard to believe they'd betray me.
這些人 我對他們了如指掌
These people, I've known them all my life.
我小時候 就已經認識埃克塞特了
Exeter's been a friend of mine since I was a boy.
你記得格林威治嗎 那次的圣誕節 那場雪仗
Do you remember Greenwich, that Christmas? The snowball fight?
要怪只能怪他老婆
It's the wife who's to blame.
看起來是柔情似水 風騷尤物
She's fickle and weak, like all her sex.
- 但其實滿腹心機 蛇蝎心腸  - 原諒她吧 寫封信寬慰她
- Easily led into scheming. - Forgive her. Write her a pardon.
讓這些人對您充滿感激之情
Put these people under a debt of gratitude to you.
這種人要是得到您的原諒 那我們豈不都被當傻子耍嗎
If you forgive them, they'll play us for fools.
大人 我可不是這么想
I don't think so, my lord.
- 現在他們的一舉一動 都逃不過我的雙眼   - 波利家也是嗎？
- Everything they do now, they do under my eye.  - And the Poles?
是的 我認為他們也應該得到寬恕
Well, I don't think they should be allowed to assume
- 他們會被寬恕的    -格林威治！
- they'll be pardoned.  - Greenwich!
那年圣誕節  大雪深及膝蓋
That Christmas, the snow was knee-deep.
亨利 那時 我們都還年輕著
Christ, we were young then, Harry.
你和那個女孩 漂流到紫杉木下 就找不到方向了 足足半小個小時
You got lost in that drift under the yew tree for half an hour
她叫什么名字來著 誰誰誰的女兒
with that girl. What's her name? So-and-so's daughter.
你打算怎么處置這些控訴
How will you frame the charges?
一般的律師不會和那些說自己能飛
Well, the common law doesn't deal with women who say they can fly
或復活的瘋女人打交道
or bring back the dead.
主犯以叛國罪論處
Treason for the principals.
從犯 終身監禁 財產充公 罰款
For the accessories, life imprisonment, confiscations, fines.
我相信國王是仁慈的
I think the King will be merciful.
相比這些 我倒是對那些舉報謀反消息的人更感興趣
I'm more interested in unravelling the plans of these people.
反正我是清白的
Well, I'm clear anyway.
你知道我是清白的對吧
You know I'm clear!
你還記得 你是怎么把國王比喻成一頭溫順的獅子嗎
Do you remember how you used to compare the King to a tamed lion?
只要你愿意 你可以親撫他 提拉他的耳朵
You can pet him, you can pull at his ears if you wish.
但你一直以來 都是在自說自話的
But all the time you're thinking to yourself...
它的爪子 看看它的爪子
..those claws, look at those claws.
我們打算提議 繼承人發案
We're putting a Bill of Succession forward,
確立安妮為亨利的合法妻子
recognising Anne as Henry's lawful wife
而他們的孩子也將是合法繼承人
and their children as the rightful heirs.
如果法案通過的話
If the bill succeeds, and it will,
我們很樂意蓋戳 宣誓
we'd like to seal the act with an oath.
什么樣的法律需要通過宣誓確立？
What sort of legislation needs to be confirmed by an oath?
好吧 信不信由你
Well, believe it or not,
那些知道該怎樣立法的人都會被留在羅馬
there are those who will feel such matters should be left to Rome.
我們想明確表示 羅馬在英格蘭
We want to make it clear that Rome has no legitimate voice
沒有合法發言權
here in England.
所以 你為什么不直接去簽署誓約呢
So, why don't you sign the oath?
毫無疑問地獻上你的忠心
Put your loyalty beyond doubt.
她看起來好像很享受被關注的感覺
She seems to be rather enjoying the attention.
也許那是她一直都想要的
Perhaps that's all she ever wanted.
和我回家吃晚飯
Come home for dinner with me.
如果你只是想款待我吃喝 當然沒問題
Well, I would if you only wanted to put food in my mouth.
但恐怕你也更喜歡用你的一堆大道理來款待我吧
But I think you'd like to put words there, too.
你提到了我的死亡
You mention my death.
‘如果親愛的王后
"If it should happen, your said dear
摯愛的妻子 安妮 升天而去...'
"and beloved wife, Queen Anne, to decease..."
我不能排除這種可能性
I can't exclude the possibility.
你說如果我死了 他就可以另選王后
You say that if I die, he can put another queen in my place.
我無法想象有其他人替代你的場景 親愛的
I can't imagine anyone else in your place, sweetheart.
這一切只是假設性的
It's notional only.
那如果她有兒子呢
And what if she has a son?
她的兒子會繼承王位 那么我的女兒怎么樣
That son will inherit. And then what will happen to my daughter
還有她的名號
and her claim?
她仍是英格蘭的公主
Well, she would still be Princess of England.
你看 上面說...
Look, it says here...
上面怎么沒說西班牙的瑪麗是個私生女
And where does it say Spanish Mary is a bastard?
瑪麗夫人并沒有繼承的權利
Lady Mary is out of the line of succession,
所以您的推理是對的 原諒我的措辭
so the inference is clear. Forgive the language.
我們試圖公正地編寫法律 那樣就不會偏向任何人
We try to write the laws sparingly, so that they're not personal.
但這本來就是關乎個人的
This IS personal.
親愛的 克倫威爾為我們做的很好
Cromwell serves us well, sweetheart.
你不應該責罵他 要責罵也應該罵別人
He's not who you should rail against. There are others.
比如說斯蒂芬 伽德納
Stephen Gardiner, for one.
他曾經冒犯我
The way he has turned on me.
我討厭忘恩負義和不忠不義
I hate ingratitude. Hate disloyalty.
托馬斯 莫爾是另一個讓我失望的人
Thomas More is another one who has disappointed me.
抱歉 我先離開了 陛下
If Your Majesties will excuse me.
你的法案很針對伊麗莎白 巴頓
Your bill against Elizabeth Barton.
你應該把莫爾也加到有罪的名單里
You should add More to the list of the guilty.
陛下 托馬斯 莫爾并沒有參與其中
Thomas More is not involved, Your Majesty.
巴頓還沒被抓時 他就已經投靠我們了
He came to me even before Barton was arrested.
無論如何也要加進去
Do it anyway.
我要讓他恐懼 恐懼可以毀掉一個人
I want him frightened. Fright can unmake a man.
我曾見識過
I've seen it happen.
克倫威爾？
Cromwell?
我是不會死的 我也會給陛下生個兒子
I won't die. I'll give the King a son.
我的血脈也會一直延續下去
And I won't die.
你要我為莫爾向陛下求情
You want me to kneel down and beg for More's life?
大人 下議院并不想莫爾出現在名單里
The Commons won't like him being included on the list, my lord.
不然他們也許會反對法案
They could oppose the bill.
而且國王發誓會在他們來之前就到 他很堅持
And the King swears he'll come before them himself and insist.
那樣的話國王可能會引起公憤
He could have a very public fall.
大人如果向陛下求情 陛下一定不會拒絕您
If you begged, my lord, the King couldn't refuse you.
陛下還能全身而退
It'll allow His Majesty an honourable way back.
畢竟我們是在讓陛下
After all, we're asking him
違背他妻子的意愿
to contradict the wishes of his own wife.
的確 這是我侄女的作風
That's true. This is my niece's work.
專橫霸道的女人
Take things personally, women.
我覺得國王很喜歡這樣的女人
I think the King takes it personally.
所以說他很無能 他干嘛要關心莫爾對他的看法
Which is weak. Why should he care what More thinks of him?
你說陛下無能？
You call the King weak?
"說陛下無能" "說陛下無能"
"Call the King weak!" "Call the King weak!"
法官大人 你哪怕一次為自己說話好嗎
Speaking for yourself for once, Lord Chancellor?
你總是等到克倫威爾發言了
Usually, you wait till Cromwell speaks
才開口 "噢 你說的對 湯姆"
and then it's, "Tweet tweet, whatever you say, Tom!"
我現在要有把弩 就馬上把你該死的腦袋射下來
If I had a crossbow, I'd shoot your fucking head off!
我說過不準人進來！
I said no-one in!
托馬斯 莫爾的女婿來為他求情 大人
Thomas More's son-in-law is here to plead for him, sir.
哼
Hm.
大人？
My lord?
要讓薩爾福克大人代您接見嗎
Should we send for my Lord Suffolk instead?
不用 他的兒子快死了 他的唯一繼承人
No, his son's dying. His heir.
他得忙著和新任妻子再續香火呢
He'll have to start breeding again with his new wife.
他老婆才14歲 你們知道嗎
She's 14, you know?
他才不會讓她一個人呆著
He won't leave her alone.
我可不是從他老婆驚嚇的表情得知的
Not judging by the startled look on her face.
我要是能擺脫我老婆就好了
If only I could get rid of my wife.
大人 你已經成功經營了20年的婚姻了
My lord, you've been well married these 20 years.
是 我知道
Yes. I know.
就像把自己裝在一個灰皮袋里20年一樣
It's like placing your person inside a grizzled leather bag.
好了 我去見他女婿 如果克倫威爾和我一起的話
All right, I'll do it. If Cranmer does it, too.
這些門外漢要跪到膝蓋爛嗎
Why should the laymen wear out their joints?
她要是聽到了估計會吐血
She'll spit blood when she hears!
好吧
Very well.
把他名字從法案中除掉吧
Remove his name from the bill.
但是告訴他 必須宣誓
But tell him, he will take the oath.
還以為我要在這多耗一個小時
Thought I'd be stuck there for another hour, entreating
萬般懇求呢
and entreating.
克倫威爾！
Cromwell!
王后想她的...
The Queen has missed her...
啊
Ah.
這次 英格蘭
This time, for sure.
一定是我們的了
England is ours.
克倫！
Crom!
我不能簽誓
I can't take the oath.
但我也不會出聲反對它
But I will not speak against it.
也不會阻止任何人宣誓
And I won't try to dissuade anyone else from it.
那是不夠的 你知道的
That's not enough, and you know it's not.
這些是已經宣誓的全部的神父名單
These are the names of the priests who have all sworn to the act.
你知道的 國會議員們都...很順從
You know the members of Parliament are...conformable.
你為什么不呢
So, why not you?
這地方對我們任何人來說都不舒服
This is not a comfortable place for any of us.
比你要去的任何地方都舒服
More comfortable than where you're going.
我相信我不是去地獄的
Well, not Hell. I trust.
那么 如果你簽了這個誓約 靈魂就會被詛咒的話
So, if your soul is damned if you sign this oath,
這些人怎么辦 難道他們都被詛咒了嗎
what about all of these? Are they damned?
還是說因為你的道德品行 要比他們都高尚？
Or is your conscience so much more refined than all of theirs?
我不能談論他們的道德
I cannot speak for their conscience.
一談起道德
Well, where it is a question of conscience,
就一定會產生疑惑
there must be some doubt.
當你將為國王服務時
And when you entered the King's service,
你要起誓聽命于他
you took an oath to obey him.
所以 你難道不會對那樣的肯定和宣誓心存疑慮么?
So, won't you set your doubts against that certainty and swear?
你被任命為大主教時 你對羅馬起誓
When you were appointed archbishop, you swore an oath to Rome.
但是他們說 整個慶典上 你很少把紙疊起來
But they say, all through the ceremony, you kept a little
說你是極不樂意地起了誓
paper folded up, saying you took the oath under protest.
那也許你也能...
Then perhaps you could...?
當然 你可以那么建議 理查德 里奇
Yes, you would suggest that, Richard Riche.
我記得你年輕時的樣子 就是一個無惡不作的家伙
I remember you as a youth and you were ever a creature of vice.
但是 我不會成為那樣一個雜耍戲子
But I will not be such a juggler.
我一直敬重你
I have respected you.
從我還是個孩童 我就一直敬重你
Since I was a boy, I have respected you.
但是后來我寧愿眼見自己親生骨肉被殺 也不愿見你拒絕簽署
But I'd sooner see my own son killed, than see you refuse to sign
這份誓言 去討好英格蘭的每一個敵人
this oath and give comfort to every enemy of England.
噢 格雷戈里是個好小伙
Oh, Gregory is a good boy.
別想他離開
Do not wish him away.
我們不能讓你回家
We can't let you go home.
我還能再見到我女兒么?
Will I see my daughter again?
只能再說幾句話 就這么多
Just have to say some words, that's all.
啊 就幾句話
Ah, just words.
出于好奇 你是行何種惡事的家伙
Out of interest, of what vices are you a creature?
我曾經也只是個小男孩
I was a boy.
但是如今 他見不得我不爭取去當牧師
But to this day, he can't see me without trying to make me a sermon.
他至少要給出理由
He should at least give his reasons.
我們知道他的理由 整個歐洲都知道他的理由
We know his reasons. All of Europe knows his reasons.
他反對離婚
He's against the divorce.
他不相信國王能夠成為教會的首腦
He doesn't believe the King can be Head of the Church.
他心屬羅馬 而非英格蘭
His heart is with Rome, not with England.
他寧愿看到統治我們的君主強加給我們的一些異邦人
He'd sooner see some foreigner imposed by the Emperor
也不愿支持一個自小就是他摯友的人
ruling us than back a man who has been his friend since childhood
你知道我最恨什么嗎?
and do you know what I hate most?
他在撰寫一份當前局勢的文章讓整個歐洲來看
He's writing an account of today for all of Europe to read
文中 我們都是愚昧之人和壓迫者
and in it, we'll be the fools and oppressors,
而他是個用精妙的措辭包裝起來的可憐受害者
and he'll be the poor victim with the better turn of phrase.
他數年前就寫了這個劇
He wrote this play years ago,
每次我臺詞不順 他都會嗤笑我
and he sniggers every time I trip over my lines.
你覺得女王的孩子未來如何
Do you think it's already been decided
現在已經能確定嗎
what the Queen's baby will be?
還是上帝自由安排
Or does God decide later?
我希望我們能在里面見她 這樣我們就能說話了
I wish we could see inside her, so we'd be able to tell.
我倒希望你就呆在威爾特郡
I wish you were down in Wiltshire.
我想要個孩子
I'd like a baby.
注意點 你肚子一旦顯形 他們會把你活埋的
Watch yourself. If your belly shows, they'll brick you up alive.
不過 你的家人也許會給你獻上祭花的
Although, your family would probably give you a bouquet.
他們不知道在狼廳 應該有怎樣的自制力
They don't know what continence is down at Wolf Hall.
我無冒犯之意
I meant no harm.
天啊 這就像在引誘一只田鼠 我...
God, it's like baiting a field mouse. I...
王后怎么樣了
How is the Queen?
我聽說了她孩子沒保住
I heard of her loss.
今天必須要做決定
It's a yes or no today.
你必須要開口
You must speak.
如果我對你的誓約說"不" 那么我就置自身于險境
If I say "no" to your oath, I put my body in peril.
如果我說"是" 則是置靈魂于不堪
If I say "yes", my soul.
所以 我什么也不說
So, I say nothing.
費舍爾主教比你更男人
Bishop Fisher is more of a man than you.
他宣布不信奉國教 并承擔了后果
He declares his dissent and takes the consequences.
你想當個賣國賊 但是又躲在沉默之中
You want to be a traitor, but hide behind silence.
非也 他想的是成為殉道者
No, what he wants is to be a martyr.
而我只是想回歸故里
What I want is to go home.
我永遠不懂犧牲和自殺之間
I've never understood where the line is drawn between sacrifice
的界限在哪
and self-slaughter.
基督界定的
Christ drew it.
你沒發現這個對比里有什么錯么?
You don't find anything wrong in the comparison?
我不傷害任何人
I do nobody harm.
我所言者無害 我所思者亦無害
I say none harm, I think none harm.
如果這還不足以支撐一個人活下去
If this isn't enough to keep a man alive...
你不會傷害任何人 那比爾尼呢 拜納姆呢
You do nobody harm? What about Bilney? What about Bainham?
你還記得你在自己家里折磨的詹姆斯 拜納姆嗎
You remember James Bainham who you had racked in your own home?
那個被你暴打虐待的人
That you had beaten and abused?
他的軀體支離破碎 他們不得不用椅子抬著他
His body was so broken they had to carry him,
到史密斯菲爾德去火化掉
carry him in the chair to Smithfield to be burned!
還有你說 托馬斯 莫爾 你不會傷害任何人嗎
And you say, Thomas More, you do no-one harm?
你要學會感恩 先生
You just be grateful, sir,
感恩我們沒有對你施加 那些你用在別人身上的手段
that we have spared you the methods you use on others.
我們會進行公訴和審訊 國王也很樂意如此的
It's the King's pleasure that we move to indictment and trial.
我在朗伯斯做服務生時 [坎特伯雷大主教官邸]
When I was a serving boy, at Lambeth,
有晚我給你帶了面包
I brought you bread one night.
你那時肯定只有14歲左右
You must have been about 14.
他們已經說你是位卓越的學者了
They were already speaking about you being the great scholar.
我記得你當時在看書
You were reading, I remember.
我問你書里有什么
I asked you what was in the book...
...而你說...
..and you said...
"文字...
"Words...
"..文字...
"..words...
"..文字而已"
"..just words."
我已經和你說了 我不記得那時見過你
As I have already told you, I have no recollection of meeting you then.
不 為什么你會不記得
No. Why would you?
聽說你的汀代爾被抓了
Hear your Tyndale's been caught.
他們說有人把他從藏身之處引出來了 一些特工...
They say someone tempted him from his hiding place, some agent...
...然后他被帶走了
..and he was taken.
你的人 不 當然不是
Your man? No, of course not.
托馬斯 莫爾不會傷害任何人
Thomas More hurts no-one.
開門
Yes.
"都是因為我"
"It's all because of me."
最后當你背叛了莫爾 困擾著他那唯一良心的
When, finally, you have out of More, what troubles his singular
你會發現是他不會對我的女王身份屈膝
conscience, you'll find it's that he won't bend his knee to my queenship.
費舍爾一日不死 我就沒有安生日子
I have no peace until Fisher is dead.
莫爾一日不死 我也不得安寧
I have no peace until More is dead.
英格蘭將永無寧日
England will have no peace.
托馬斯 莫爾 請求羅馬君主侵略我們 我知道
Thomas More prays for the Emperor to invade us. I know this.
你知道 他也知道 只是他不會承認
You know this. He knows it, but he won't admit it.
他曾是我朋友
He was my friend.
但是 眼下 當英格蘭身處險境
And yet, now, in this time of danger for England,
當你需要他的支持 他卻去迎合敵人
when you need his support, he gives comfort to the enemy.
他的沉默 他所依賴的沉默中
This silence of his, on which he relies.
隱藏著叛國野心 所以 逼他開口
It conceals treason. So, MAKE him talk.
不 夫人 我們不必這么做
No, madam, we don't do that.
我的妻子她...
My wife is...
...她的悲傷...
..her grief...
我理解
Yes.
我歸咎于凱瑟琳
It's Katherine I blame.
這么些年來她都沒有誕下一個子嗣
All those years she couldn't hold a son.
而現在她也在詛咒我
Now, she ill-wishes me.
她冷血的阻攔在我和我愛的女人之間
She lies in between me and the woman I love, with her cold heart...
你知道嗎 我連那嬰兒是男是女都沒看到 就被他們火化了
You know they burnt it before I could see if it was a boy.
這可能真的很難斷定 陛下
It may have been impossible to tell, Your Majesty.
畢竟事情發生如此突然
So soon.
這個 額 托馬斯 莫爾的這件事
This, erm... This business of Thomas More.
我不懷疑他對羅馬的絕對忠心
I don't doubt his loyalty to Rome,
也不懷疑他對陛下成為教會首腦的憎惡
or his hatred of Your Majesty's title as Head of the Church.
然而 從合法性上來看 我們的案件很麻煩
However, legally, our case is slender.
不會很容易
It won't be easy.
我留你在這是為了讓你解決容易的事么?
Do I keep you for what's easy?
你認為我提拔你是因為你的儀態魅力嗎？
Do you think I've promoted you for the charm of your presence?
我讓你留在這是因為你是個聰明人
I keep you because you're a serpent.
別反咬一口
Do not be a viper in my bosom.
你知道我的決定 立即執行
You know my decision. Execute it.
壁畫上的那個女人
That woman on the wall.
我知道她是誰
I know who she is.
示巴王后
Sheba.
對于你 我明白她在你心中的位置
For you. I know who she is for you.
明白你的目光永遠停留在她身上的原因
Why you always look at her.
在安特衛普省他們告訴了我
They told me about her in Antwerp.
克倫威爾愛著的女人
The woman Cromwell loved.
為什么你不回去追求她
Why don't you go back and claim her?
她已嫁做人婦
She's married.
很多年了
It was years ago.
我也變了
I've changed.
呀 你現在很富有
Ja. You're rich now.
我想...
I think...
嗯？
What?
沒什么
Nothing.
怎么? 你要把我吊起來直到我開口么?
What? You're going to hang me up by my wrists until I talk?
我想你心中肯定另有佳人了
I think there is another woman in your heart now.
托馬斯 莫爾的妻子求見
Thomas More's wife is here to see you.
愛麗絲女士
Lady Alice.
我之前來的時候 這就是個陳舊陰冷的古樓房
When I came here before, this was a musty old place.
我丈夫常和我說
My husband used to say,
"將托馬斯 克倫威爾投進地牢而到傍晚
"Put Thomas Cromwell in a dungeon and by evening,
他就會坐在墊子上 而監獄長還欠著他錢"
"he'll be sitting on cushions, with gaolers owing him money."
他說過要把我投進地牢嗎
Did he talk a lot about putting me in dungeons?
他...只是空談
He... It was only talk.
我想你可以帶我去覲見國王
I thought you might take me to see the King.
他對女人都非常友善
I know he's always kind to women.
我做不到 我到希望可以
I can't do that. I wish I could.
你對我們一直都很好 我知道原因
You've always been good to us. I wonder why.
你經常會耍一些伎倆
You always have some trick.
天生的小伎倆是幫不了忙的
Born tricky. Can't help it.
愛麗絲 為什么你的丈夫那么冥頑不固
Alice, why is your husband so stubborn?
我對他的了解 不比對三位一體了解的多
I no more understand him than I do the Holy Trinity.
他擔心他太冷漠
I worry he's cold.
他什么都不和我講
He tells me nothing.
他所有的信都是給他的寶貝梅格
All his letters are to his precious Meg.
當然也不要認為我們之間沒有了溫情
Don't think there's no tenderness between us.
我們有交易的 雖然時間說不定
We had dealings, one time or another.
當那既成事實 你根本沒法幫上忙只能為他擔心
And when that's true, you can't help but worry about a man,
想想...
wonder if...
想想如果他感情淡漠時
wonder if he's feeling cold.
當你和他談話 問問他我的事
When you talk to him, ask him from me...
問他 孤身一人離開發妻當真明智么
Ask him, does he think it's clever to leave his wife without company,
他的兒子無所忠告 他的女兒無所庇護
his son without advice, his daughter without protection?
我們所有人聽憑于像他一樣的人
And all of us at the mercy of a man like yourself?
我們必須帶走你所有的筆 紙還有你的書籍
We have to take away your pens and papers and your books.
好吧 如果你一定要帶走他們 就現在吧
Very well. If you must take them, take them now.
愛麗絲來見我 她希望你回家
Alice came to see me. She wants you home.
你所需要做的事就是簽了這個字 梅格已經簽過了
All you have to do, is sign this. Meg has signed it.
你最愛的女兒
Your own beloved daughter.
快簽了這個吧 國王會為此高興的
Just sign the paper and the King will be happy.
我會安排我的船 將你送回切爾西
I'll send my barge to row you back to Chelsea,
回到你的家園 你的孩子身邊 回到愛麗絲夫人身邊
back to your garden, your children, back to Dame Alice
那個一直等你歸家 獨守空閨的女人
who will be waiting to bear you up to your own bed.
難道你不想嗎
Don't you want that?
難道你不想逃離這個鬼地方嗎
Don't you want to be out of this place you're in?
當我們在天堂重相遇時...
When we meet again in Heaven...
...當然 我希望我們可以相遇...
...as I hope we will...
...我們之間所有的差異都蕩然無存了
..all our differences will be forgot.
但現在 我們還不能忽視差異的存在
But, for now, we cannot wish them away.
我現在僅有的 就是我所站立的這片土地
All I have, all I own is the ground I stand upon.
這片土地是我托馬斯 莫爾的
That ground is Thomas More.
如果你想占有它 你必須將它從我這里奪走
If you want it, you must take it.
我也不會輕易將它舍棄的
I will not yield it.
當你上庭前你來到這里
When you come before the court,
將你沐浴在王的仁慈之下
throw yourself upon the King's mercy.
陛下并不是一個兇殘的人 你知道的
He's not a cruel man, you know that.
我怎么知道
Do I?
最起碼他不是一直如此的
He didn't used to be.
雖然他后來更換了他的隨從們
But then he's changed the company he keeps.
隨便吧
Anyway...
折磨我的肢體什么的都不重要了
It's not important what happens to my body.
難道你不害怕疼痛嗎
Are you not afraid of the pain?
噢 當然 我很害怕
Oh, yes. I'm very much afraid.
我并不是一個強壯 有精力的人 就像你一樣
I am not a strong and robust man, such as yourself.
我無能為力 只能在腦海里想象
I cannot help but rehearse it in my mind.
但也只感受了一小會兒
But I will only feel it for a moment,
而后上帝也不會讓我記住這感受的
and God will not let me remember it afterwards.
我將離你而去 你知道嗎
I would have left you, you know...
遠離你的生活之外
..to live out your life...
為你的殘酷贖罪
..to repent your cruelties...
如果我是國王的話
..if I were king.
帶走他的書籍
Take away his books.
我將會送給別人
I'll send someone.
不 理查德 我想讓你親自去做
No, Richard, I'd like you to do it yourself.
如果陪審團審判下來 陛下會讓我們扒皮抽筋的
If the jury throws it out, the King will skin us alive.
不 王后會的
No. The Queen will.
天啊 看起來好像對他施了鞭刑
My God, looks like we've had him whipped.
他說我從不浪費一次騙局
And he says I never miss a trick.
如果他繼續保持沉默...
If he stands on his silence...
他的沉默證明不了任何事
His silence proves nothing.
他不用證明什么 大人
He doesn't have to prove anything, my lord.
他的愿望就是他的沉默
His plea is that his silence is consent enough
能讓國王足夠滿意
to the King's desires.
一派胡言
Bollocks.
這是習慣法的準則
It is the maxim of the common law.
還在胡扯
Still bollocks.
他還沒有完全噤聲
He hasn't been entirely silent.
我過來拿走你的書
I came to take away your books.
我這么做的時候 我試圖說服你 這是你最后一次起誓的機會
And as I did so, I tried to convince you one last time to take the oath.
我給你立案了 對嗎
I put a case to you, did I not?
我問過你 如果議會舉行投票并讓我做國王...
I asked you, if Parliament had a vote and made me king...
...你會贊同嗎
..would you go along with it?
然后你說 "最近議會無論做什么事
And you said, "Nothing that Parliament would do,
都不會讓我吃驚"
"would surprise me these days.
"但是 如果他們票選 理查德 里奇 成為上帝"
"But, if they voted that Richard Riche should be God,
"我就劃清界限 到此為止"
"I would draw a line there."
我問你為什么 你還記得你怎么回答的嗎
I asked you why? Do you remember your reply?
我對此沒有任何記錄 沒有任何書面材料
I made no record of it, having no writing materials.
你已經把材料從我身邊拿走了
You having already taken them from me.
你說"議會不能這么做
You said, "Parliament cannot do it.
法律只能在世俗的世界有效 而不能在天堂"
"It can make laws in the earthly realm, not the heavenly."
所以我說 "這不能使我成為上帝 或者是教會首腦
So I said, "It could not make me God, nor Head of the Church, either,
"但這確實無疑是精神上的管制壓迫"
"for surely that is a spiritual jurisdiction?"
你說"不 議會不能那樣做"
And you said, "No, Parliament cannot do it."
是什么意思呢
Meaning what?
意思是 如果議會宣布將國王任命為教會首腦
Meaning, if Parliament names the King the Head of the Church,
是不具備法律效力的
it has no effect.
據托馬斯爵士所言
According to Sir Thomas.
他否認了國王的頭銜
He denied the King's title.
這屬于叛國罪
That would be treason.
請大家捫心自問 先生們
Ask yourselves, gentlemen,
我為什么要對理查德 里奇這種人敞開心扉呢
why would I open my mind to a man like Richard Riche?
為什么 當學者和神職人員都懇求我的時候
Why, when the learned and the pious have implored me,
當國王自己因為一些重要的原因來說服我的時候
when the King himself with weighty reasons has sought to persuade me.
因為你覺得我不重要
Because you think I don't matter.
這就是你說的
That is what you said.
我會對此起誓的
I will take my oath on it.
你起誓？  你的誓言還不如魔鬼的屁!
Your oath? Your oath isn't worth the Devil's fart!
上帝保佑你 里奇 我認識你的時候 你還是個孩子
Christ help you, Riche, I have known you since you were a child,
你的家庭都對你失望了 你是一個賭徒 一個廢物
you were the despair of your family, you were a gambler and a waster.
我要提醒你 理查德 里奇 現在是律師總管
May I remind you that Richard Riche is Solicitor General,
你不能像對待酒館侍者一樣議論他
and not to be talked to like some pot-boy.
你說的什么可以的話嗎?
Did you speak the words alleged?
我對此表示懷疑 如果我說了...
I doubt it, and if I did...
- 如果你說了   - 如果我說了 他們肯定不吝指控我的
- If you did?  - If I did, they were not meant with malice.
所以 法官大人們 你不能認定他們是合理的
And so, masters, you cannot find them treasonable
而且你應當蔑視謠言
and you are bound to disregard such words,
無論法庭對你說什么
whatever this court tells you.
罪犯 這個法庭發現你有叛國行為
Prisoner, this court has found you guilty of treason.
你的審判將在...
Your sentence will be...
請原諒我 罪犯還有什么要說的嗎
Forgive me. Does the prisoner have anything to say?
我遵從了我的良知
I have followed my conscience.
請你也一定遵從你的良心
You must follow yours.
我已履行的良知 現在我要簡單地說兩句
My conscience satisfies me and now, I will speak plainly,
你的法令是錯誤的 你的權力也毫無根基
that your statute is faulty and your authority baseless.
我的良知與大多數人一樣
My conscience stands with the majority.
抵制亨利的王朝 我擁有的是基督世界所有王國的支持
Against Henry's kingdom, I have all the kingdoms of Christendom!
你現在已經暴露了你的野心 先生!
Now we see your malice, sir!
反對你的每一個主教...
Against each one of your bishops...
現在我們看到的是 你選擇的羅馬而不是英格蘭!
Now, we see you choose Rome over England!
- 反對你的議會 先生!  - 你這個叛徒!
- Against your Parliament!  - You traitor!
我擁有教會所有委員會
I have all the general councils of the Church,
將在這一切的背后蔓延千年!
stretching back for a thousand years!
這是他最后時刻帶在身邊的的祈禱書
It's the prayer book he had with him at the end.
您并沒有選擇 大人
You had no choice, master.
托馬斯?
Thomas?
莉茲
Liz.
托馬斯 這是喬安娜
Thomas? It's Johane.
你發燒了
You have a fever.
莉茲 讓我...
Liz, let me...
讓我去愛她
Let me love her.
讓我去愛她 莉茲
Let me love her, Liz.
快去找巴茨大人來
Fetch Dr Butts.
是我在意大利患上的一種發燒癥狀
It's a fever I got in Italy.
那有條蛇
It was a snake.
就是這樣
Let's say it is.
如果我快死了...
If I'm dying...
...找格雷戈里來
..get Gregory.
格雷戈里 有些事我要告訴他
Gregory, there's things I need to tell him.
慢點 這樣我就能看見你是怎么做的了
Slow down, so I can see how you do it.
我不能慢下來
I can't slow down.
如果我停下來去想我在怎么做 我就會做不起來
If I stop to think how I'm doing it, I won't be able to do it.
到了國王夏季旅行的時候
Itinerary for the King's summer progress.
離開溫莎 然后去雷丁 米森登 阿賓登
Depart Windsor, then to Reading, Missenden, Abingdon.
我們在薩德利加入他們
We join them at Sudley.
如果我們在18號離開...
If we leave on the 18th...?
提前一天出發 路況不好
Leave a day earlier. The roads.
好的 先去格洛斯特 然后去索恩伯里
Yes.Gloucester then to Thornbury.
鐵阿克頓村 布朗厄姆
Iron Acton. Bromham.
九月下旬去溫徹斯特和華爾頓主教
Late September, Winchester, Bishop's Waltham.
先生?
Sir?
去布朗厄姆之前 再加一處地方
Before Bromham, add another.
什么?
Yes?
九月初
Early September.
在狼廳 待五天
Five days Wolf Hall.
約翰爵士
Sir John.
陛下 歡迎光臨舍下
Majesty. Welcome.
我的騎馬帽遺失了
Lost my hat riding here.
我會讓仆人去找回的 陛下
I'll send servants to find it, Your Highness.
彼以國士待我，我以國士待之，用過免費優質字幕服務，
而又有能力的人，有義務將這個免費服務做下去若有心加入我們 聯系：dajiazimuzu@163.com